Finding Aid for Extension Service (University of Michigan) records, 1911-1999
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Central Office Files
  - Area Office Records
    - Detroit
      - Day Care Committee 1942 (Box 52)
      - Defense Gardening 1941 (Box 52)
      - Graduate School circa 1939-1940 (Box 52)
      - Great Lakes Adult Education Conference 1939 (Box 52)
      - Institutes 1942 (Box 52)
      - Michigan Industrial Training Council 1942-1943 (Box 52)
      - Program Planners Institute 1940 (Box 52)
    - Flint
      - Historical Development 1944-1953 (Box 29)
      - Correspondence and Memos
        - 1944-1947 (Box 29)
        - 1948-1950 (Box 29)
        - 1951-1952 (Box 29)
        - 1953-1954 (Box 29)
        - 1955-1956 (Box 29)
        - 1957-1958 (Box 29)
        - 1959-1964 (Box 29)
      - General Motors "AC" Sparkplug 1956-1963, 2 folders (Box 29)
      - General Motors-Buick Division 1957-1960 (Box 29)
    - Grand Rapids
      - Historical Development 1943-1953, 1943-1968 (Box 29)
      - Area Reports
        - 1961-1962 (Box 29)
        - 1963-1964 (Box 29)
      - Arts Program 1956-1961 (Box 29)
      - Office Correspondence
        - 1943-1949 (Box 29)
        - 1948-1950 (Box 29)
        - 1951-1952 (Box 29)
        - 1953-1954 (Box 29)
        - 1955-1959 (Box 29)
        - 1960-1963 (Box 30)
        - 1964-1971 (Box 30)
        - 1971-1973 (Box 30)
      - Calvin College Proposal 1967-1969 (Box 30)
      - Policy Manual 1949 (Box 30)
      - Studies and Surveys 1951-1957 (Box 30)
      - Student Objectives 1959-1961 (Box 30)
      - Suggested Program 1960-1963 (Box 30)
      - Correspondence, Minutes, etc. 1971-1973 (Box 52)
    - Muskegon 1948-1961 (Box 30)
    - Pontiac 1951-1956 (Box 30)
    - Port Huron 1957-1963 (Box 30)
    - Saginaw Area
      - Histories (Box 30)
      - Alpena-Bay City (Box 30)
      - Cadillac-Midland (Box 30)
      - Office Correspondence
        - 1945-1959 (Box 30)
        - 1959-1962 (Box 30)
      - Coordinating Council for Higher Education 1978-1981 (Box 52)
    - Traverse City
      - Crystal Lake Art Program, Frankfort (Box 30)
      - Office Correspondence
        - 1948-1952 (Box 30)
        - 1953-1954 (Box 30)
        - 1954-1955 (Box 30)
        - 1955-1956 (Box 30)
        - 1957-1958 (Box 30)
        - 1959-1962, 2 folders (Box 30)
      - Petoskey (Box 30)
      - Northwest Michigan Inter-Institutional Committee 1971-1973 (Box 52)
    - Upper Peninsula
      - Historical Development (Box 31)
      - Centennial at the Soo 1956 (Box 31)
      - Community Concert Report 1956-1958 (Box 31)
      - Cooperative Field Courses 1958-1959 (Box 31)
      - Ironwood, Michigan 1946-1950 (Box 31)
      - Northern Michigan College 1958 (Box 31)
      - Office Correspondence
        - 1946-1947, 2 folders (Box 31)
        - 1948 (Box 31)
        - 1949 (Box 31)
        - 1950-1952 (Box 31)
        - 1952-1954 (Box 31)
        - 1955-1957 (Box 31)
        - 1957-1958 (Box 31)
        - 1959-1960 (Box 31)
        - 1961-1962 (Box 31)
        - 1963 (Box 31)
        - 1964 (Box 31)
      - Progress Report 1956 (Box 31)
      - Proposal for Improved Service 1958 (Box 31)
      - Sault Ste. Marie 1957 (Box 31)
      - Stephenson, Michigan 1948-1949 (Box 31)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Adult Education Association, USA 1963-1980 (Box 32)
    - Adult Education Act of 1966 (Box 32)
    - State Technical Service Act of 1965 (Box 32)
    - Higher Education Act of 1965 (Box 32)
    - Higher Education Act of 1965 (cont.) (Box 33)
  - Course, Lecture and Instructor Files
    The Course, Lecture and Instructor Files consists mainly of card file indexes to extension courses and lectures, dated approximately 1911 to 1981. The cards include name of instructor, subject, date and location of the course or lecture.
    - Card File of course instructors
      - circa 1954-1969 (Box 34)
        (arranged alphabetically by name, and including name of course, location, and stipend)
      - circa 1954-1981 (Box 35)
    - Card File of extension lectures (Box 36)
      - circa 1911-1956 [arranged alphabetically by location, and including date, name of instructor] (2 card sequences) (Box 36)
    - Card File of extension lectures [arranged chronologically, includes information on subject, lecturer, date, place]
      - 1920/21-1923/24 (Box 36)
      - 1923/1924-1930/1931 (doctors) (Box 37)
      - Lectures 1930/31-1935/36 (Box 38)
      - 1935/36, 1946/47 (Box 39)
        [begin arrangement by location, speaker, date]
      - 1947/48-1955/56 (Box 40)
      - 1955/56, 1959/60 (Box 41)
      - 1960/61-1963/64 (Box 42)
      - 1963/64, 1968/69 (Box 43)
      - 1969/70-1980/81 (Box 44)
    - Card File, arranged alphabetically by name, of course grades for Industrial Engineering Program circa 1957-1970 (Box 45)
    - Roster of Instructors and Courses Offered 1974/75-1978/79 (Box 50)
  - Personnel Files
    [CLOSED EXCEPT WITH WRITTEN PERMISSION OF DONOR]
    - Personnel Files (Box 46)
    - Personnel Files (Box 47)
      (continued)
    - Personnel Files (Box 48)
    - Personnel Files (Box 49)
- Histories
  The Histories series includes both brief sketches and more extended treatments of the development of the Extension Service and its various sub-units. These were written between the 1930s and the 1970s. Additional histories of individual area offices may be found under the names of the respective cities in the Central Office Files.
  - undated, 1930s (Box 50)
  - 1940-1959 (Box 50)
  - 1960-1969 (Box 50)
  - Extracts From Regents Proceedings Regarding Extension Service (Box 50)
- Firemanship Training Program (Box 54)
  The Firemanship Training Program series is composed mostly of material relating to the education of fire personnel and includes mostly course material. The series is divided into several subseries; Background, Correspondence, Fire Schools, Seminars and Conferences, Civil Defense and Disaster Training Center, and Topical Files. Photographs relating to these materials may be found in the Audiovisual series
  - Background
    The Background subseries contains material relating to the founding of the program and its expansion after the construction of the new facility. Included in this series are correspondence, reports, newspaper clippings and magazine articles. The Correspondence subseries provides information about the later years of the program from 1976 to 1990. It is arranged in chronological order.
    - General (Box 54)
    - Firemanship Training History & Planning 1956, 1959 (Box 54)
    - Newspaper Clippings & Magazine Articles (Box 54)
  - Correspondence
    - 1976-1981, 6 folders (Box 54)
    - 1984, 1988-1990 (Box 54)
  - Fire Schools
    The two largest subseries are Fire Schools and Seminars and Conferences. These two series contain materials relating to the main focus of the program, fire fighter training and education. The Fire Schools subseries contains announcement brochures, enrollment numbers, course schedules and material, exams, lecture guides and instructor's manuals. Information is provided on basic, intermediate and advanced fire schools, the 240-hour academy, industrial fire brigades and town and regional fire schools. The material is arranged alphabetically by topic or type of school.
    - Announcement Brochures (Box 54)
    - Academic Evaluation Forms (Box 54)
    - Annual Reports 1968-1972, 1974-1978 (Box 54)
    - Associate in Firemanship Training Job Description 1968 (Box 54)
    - Course Materials
      - Advanced Firemanship Program (Box 54)
      - Fire Problems (Box 54)
      - Exams, 2 folders (Box 54)
      - Instructor's Manual in Elementary Fire Service Training 1951 (Box 54)
      - Lesson Outlines, 4 folders (Box 54)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 54)
      - 240 Hour Academy
        - 1981 (Box 54)
        - Instructor's Guide
          - Phase 2, 2 folders (Box 54)
          - Phase 3, 3 folders (Box 54)
    - Course Schedules (Box 54)
    - Fire Detection & Arson Investigation 1980 (Box 54)
    - Industrial Fire Brigade
      - Program Outline (Box 54)
      - 1979-1981, 3 folders (Box 54)
      - Detroit-Edison 1977, 1979-1981 (Box 54)
      - Ford Hospital 1979-1980 (Box 54)
      - Ford Motor Company 1977, 1979, 1981 (Box 54)
    - Town Schools
      - Basic Fire Training Curriculum (Box 54)
      - Intermediate Fire Training Curriculum (Box 54)
      - Advanced Fire Training Curriculum (Box 54)
      - Monthly Statistics 1967-1981, 2 folders (Box 54)
      - Press Releases 1978 (Box 54)
  - Seminars and Conferences
    The Seminars and Conferences subseries contains handouts, course material, and announcement brochures. Offerings included: fire chiefs training, fire instructors training, fire detection and arson investigation, industrial fire control, and state property fire control. This subseries is arranged alphabetically by type of seminar and then chronologically by date of the seminar.
    - Announcement Brochures, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Fire Chief's Conference 1981 (Box 55)
    - EMS in the Fire Service 1979-1980, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Michigan Fire Chief's Conference (Box 55)
    - Fireman Officers' Training Conference, Course Materials, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Fireman Officers' Training Conference, Upper Peninsula 1961 (Box 55)
    - Firemen Instructors' Training Conference
      - Course Materials
        - Undated, 2 folders (Box 55)
        - 1949-1954, 1958-1959 (Box 55)
        - March 18-20, 1958 (Box 55)
        - October 16-21, 1977 (Box 55)
        - February 19-21, 1980 (Box 55)
        - February 17-19, 1981 (Box 55)
    - Regional Arson Seminars 1968/69-1971/72, 1976/77 (Box 55)
    - Fire Detection & Arson Investigation Seminar
      - March 2-4, 1976 (Box 55)
      - March 7-9. 1978 (Box 55)
      - March 6-8, 1979 (Box 55)
      - March 4-6, 1980 (Box 55)
    - Fire Apparatus Supervisors Seminar 1976 (Box 55)
    - Fire Department Administrators Seminar
      - 1961 (Box 55)
      - 1967 (Box 55)
    - Industrial Fire Control Seminar 1976-1980, 5 folders (Box 55)
    - State Property Fire Safety Seminar 1959-1962, 4 folders (Box 55)
  - Civil Defense and Disaster Training Center (Fire Building)
    The Civil Defense and Disaster Training Center subseries relates to the fire training center and its many uses. Information is provided on the building itself, the uses of the building and its history. Material consists mainly of correspondence and some reports.
    - Planning
      - 1955-1959, 2 folders (Box 56)
      - Meeting Minutes 1956-1958, 2 folders (Box 56)
      - Technical Committee 1956-1957 (Box 56)
      - Use
        - 1959-1965 (Box 56)
        - Ann Arbor Fire Department 1957, 1965-1966, 1969, 1978, 1981 (Box 56)
  - Topical Files
    The Topical Files subseries contains some office files and material on other activities of the program and is arranged alphabetically. Included in this subseries is material relating to the publication and film, "The Firefighter and Electrical Equipment."
    - Civil Disturbance (Box 56)
    - Curriculum Planning 1979-1980 (Box 56)
    - Emergency Hospital Training Unit (Box 56)
    - Fees 1978-1981 (Box 56)
    - Fire Department Organization (Box 56)
    - Fire Engines 1980-1981 (Box 56)
    - Fire Fighters Training Council 1978, 1980 (Box 56)
    - Fire Science Program 1969, 1974-1975 (Box 56)
    - Fire Service Instruction & Research Center
      - Evaluation (Box 56)
      - Future of 1979-1980 (Box 56)
      - Goals 1978/79-1979/80 (Box 56)
    - "The Fire Fighter & Electrical Equipment" Publication
      - 1948, 1952, 1959-1960, 2 folders (Box 56)
      - Film Project 1964 (Box 56)
    - Firemanship Training
      - 1969, 1977-1980, 2 folders (Box 56)
      - Monthly Activity Reports November 1980-March 1981 (Box 56)
    - High Rise Emergencies Course 1982 (Box 56)
    - Industrial Fire Program 1955-1957 (Box 56)
    - Integrated Fire & Police Departments 1957-1959 (Box 56)
    - International Association of Arson Investigators Arson Conference 1975-1976 (Box 56)
    - Michigan Alliance for Fire Safety 1977 (Box 56)
    - Programming 1980-1981 (Box 56)
    - Promotional Examinations 1980 (Box 56)
    - State Advisory Committee for Fireman Education 1955 (Box 56)
    - Suggested Programs (Box 56)
    - Washtenaw Fire Investigation Bureau 1980 (Box 56)
- Audiovisual Materials
  The Audiovisual Materials series contains five subseries, Audiotapes, Films, Photographs, Slides, and Video Tapes.
  - Audiotapes
    The Audiotapes subseries contains one audiotape reel that contains a lecture, ca. 1952, on the history of firemen's training in Michigan and the Extension Service's Fire College.
    - Lecture on History of Firemen's Training in Michigan, Extension Fire College 1952, one 7-inch reel, 3.75 ips (Box 57)
      (possibly by R. C. Loughead)
  - Films
    The Films subseries contains one film, "Learning For Living," produced ca. 1944, which documents the work of the Extension Service. It includes brief footage of President Alexander Ruthven (silent), Extension Service Director C. A. Fisher, and E. J. Soop, then head of the Detroit office, as well as shots of the Ann Arbor campus and the Rackham Educational Memorial Building in Detroit. A phonograph recording, "The Promise of Living" by the Rackham Choir, has been transferred to the library's audio collection.
    - "Learning for Living", 16mm, b/w, ca. 18 min. (Box 57)
      (outsized location Y381B)
  - Photographs
    The Photograph subseries is located in box 57 and one outsize folder (UBImum/C470). This material is arranged alphabetically according to the subject of the photographs. All photographs are black and white and there are some negatives included with the corresponding prints.
    Ann Arbor Campus Buildings photographs include images of the Bell Tower, the Horace H. Rackham Building, interiors of the Rackham and Hill Auditoriums and an aerial view of the University of Michigan Stadium and the entire Ann Arbor campus.
    Courses and Programs photographs (prints and contact prints) contain classroom shots of the courses offered in gaming, art, Great Lakes research, adult education, real estate, and radio broadcasting, including two prints of Joseph Maddy in the WJR studio. Extension Service Centers (prints and negatives) photographs include images of Extension Service Centers in Ann Arbor (no negative), Dearborn, Detroit, Grand Rapids, Flint, and Saginaw. The Rackham Memorial Educational Building photographs also include three prints of university and city officials at the laying of the building cornerstone, and six prints of the Rackham building.
    The Firemanship training program photographs make up a large portion of the Courses and Programs photographs. The photographs are separated by topic and arranged alphabetically. The largest group of photos are the class photos for the residential schools, which range from 1959-1981. Also included are photographs of training at the Civil Defense and Disaster Center and town schools. Photographs of staff members include Wally Gannon, Francis Hartman, W. Tackaberry, B. Parrot. Arthur Appel and Robert Schultz are pictured in various class portraits.
    Staff Members includes photographs, most of them identified, of Extension Service staff, including Al Storey, Dan Brown, and William D. Henderson, Extension Services Director from 1919 to 1937. There is also a set of photographs of Everett J. Soop, Extension Services Director from 1948 to 1970.
    - Ann Arbor Campus Buildings undated, 12 prints black and white (Box 57)
      (including the Bell Tower, aerial view of the stadium, aerial view of the campus and dorm buildings)
    - Courses & Programs
      - American Red Cross "Fitness for the Future" 1962 (Box 57)
        17 8x10 b&w prints
      - Classroom Scenes
        - Interior undated, 28 prints black and white; 3 contact prints; 3 negatives (Box 57)
          (includes adult education, radio broadcasting, art classes, real estate, meat cutting, and a book discussion group) (two photos in outsize folder; location UBImum/C470)
        - Exterior undated, 4 prints black and white; 8 contact prints (Box 57)
          (includes Great Lakes research and nature history)
      - Explorer Scouts 1962, 20 prints and negatives black and white (Box 57)
      - Extension Service Orchestra & Rackham Choir, 6 prints black and white (Box 57)
        (includes photographs of the 1951 Extension Service Orchestra Christmas Concert directed by David Mattern and the Rackham Choir in concert) (one print in outsize folder; location UBImum/C470)
      - Firemanship Training Program
        - Civil Defense & Disaster Training Center, North Campus undated, 16 prints black and white (Box 57)
          (includes photos of interior and exterior, construction, emergency hospital exhibit, and the training tower)
        - Class Photos 1959-1981, 10 folders black and white (Box 57)
        - Fire College 1966, 13 prints black and white (Box 57)
        - Mt. Clemens Regional Fire School 1957, 17 prints black and white (Box 57)
        - Staff Members undated, 25 prints black and white (Box 57)
          (includes photos of Francis Hartman, Walter Gannon, W. Tackaberry, B. Parrot, Burr and Adamonski)
        - Structure Fires undated, 8 prints black and white (Box 57)
        - Training undated, 2 folders; 54 prints black and white (Box 57)
          (includes classroom scenes, fire drills, and photos of Michaelyn Maurer, first woman in the program)
      - Midwestern Music Conference 1962, 3 prints black and white 8x10 (Box 57)
      - Registration undated, 1 prints black and white; 7 contact prints black and white (Box 57)
        (depicts registration process at the Rackham building in Detroit)
    - Extension Service Centers
      - Dearborn Classroom Building, Dearborn Campus undated, 2 prints black and white; 1 negatives (Box 57)
      - Extension Services Building, Ann Arbor Campus 1961, 2 prints black and white (Box 57)
      - Mott Memorial Building, Flint Campus 1970, 3 prints black and white; 1 negatives (Box 57)
      - Rackham Memorial Educational Center, Detroit 1940, 1966, 7 prints black and white; 1 negatives (Box 57)
        (includes group shot at cornerstone laying, and building exterior) (one print of building in outsize folder; location UBImum/C470)
      - University Center, Grand Rapids undated, 2 prints black and white; 1 negatives (Box 57)
      - University Center for Adult Education (UCAE), Wayne State University undated, 1 prints with negatives black and white (Box 57)
      - Wicks Hall, Saginaw 1970, 2 prints black and white; 1 negatives (Box 57)
    - Staff Members, 35 prints black and white
      (includes photos of Alfred Story, Everett J. Soop, William D. Henderson, Harry Overstreet, Don Brown, Louise Cain, and Robben Fleming.) (one photo in outsize folder; call no. \UBImum/C470)
      - Fisher, Charles 1947 (Folder UBImum/C470)
    - Student Life undated, 11 prints black and white (Box 57)
      (including students in dorm room, studying in the libraries and socializing)
  - Slides
    The Slides subseries contains 76 color slides with an index, of Extension Service Centers in the state of Michigan as well as classroom scenes. This set may have been used for presentation purposes.
    - Extension Service Centers undated, 76 slides color (Box 57)
      (includes the Henry Ford Centennial Library, Dearborn Campus, registration activities and a map of Extension Service Centers in Michigan)
  - Video Tapes
    - Academic Outreach Video circa 1997, VHS (Box 60)
    - Hearth Video (Nursing Online Computer Mediated Communications System) 1995, VHS (Box 60)
- Academic Outreach Files
  The Academic Outreach series offers some documentation on the development of the Academic Outreach office and decisions to determine the focus and thrust of the office. Material represented here relates primarily to the extension functions continued by the successor office. Several of the files reflect efforts to utilize technology as an outreach and extension activity.
  - Administrative Files
    - Background Information 1991-1999 (Box 60)
    - Budget 1988-1999, 2 folders (Box 60)
  - Topical Files
    - Committee on Institutional Cooperation (CIC) Leadership ("Common Market" Courses) 1998 (Box 60)
    - Faculty Exploratory Workshops 1997-1998 (Box 60)
    - Intellectual Properties Task Force 1995-1996 (Box 60)
    - K-12 Projects 1997 (Box 60)
    - Miscellaneous Policy and Administrative Material 1994-1997, 2 folders (Box 60)
    - Michigan Jobs Commission 1995-1998 (Box 60)
    - Michigan Virtual Auto College 1997-1998 (Box 60)
    - Nursing 1996-1998 (Box 60)
    - Social Work 1996-1997, 2 folders (Box 60)
    - Summer Sessions 1994-1998 (Box 60)
    - University of Michigan Virtual Campus undated (Box 60)